Welcome back, and this is the last video
of Kafka consumer. And with that
our Kafka cluster, Kafka producer, Kafka
consumer will all get complete.
Okay? So, in this topic today of Kafka
consumer, what I will do is I will cover
some important configuration step by
step. So, if you remember that I have
shared with you the complete
consumer read flow. So, there are around
12 13 steps. So, today what I will go
through is go through each step and all
possible doubts and interview questions
can come on it and how to answer it. So,
let's start without wasting any time.
So, step one in the consumer
read flow. What was that? If you can
recall.
Consumer is start and want to join the
group. So, one question can come is can
a consumer join more than one group?
Answer is no. One consumer can join only
one group.
Step two was find the partition number
of the topic consumer offset. So, here
whatever the group
consumer need to join, so it find out
the partition.
Okay? Because this partition is
where all the information about this
group would be stored.
Okay, so there is nothing
uh
in this step which I can think a
question might come.
Step three.
Consumer request metadata first time.
Because see
let's say a partition 23.
Okay, this group is let's say
notification group and with this formula
there are you know that
_consumer_offset
there are how many partition 50.
So, hash of notification
group ID mod 50. Let's say you got
partition 23.
So, this is
partition 23 is the one which store all
the information about this group.
So, it need to know
which broker
holds partition 23 of consumer offset.
Right? So, it need this information. So,
first time it doesn't have this
information. It need to fetch the
metadata.
So, the question is
we already know that it calls the
bootstrap server
which ask for metadata and the bootstrap
server return the metadata. We have
already seen that flow. Now, the
question which can come is how
frequently this metadata is refreshed?
Okay?
So, there are two ways. Periodic refresh
and on-demand refresh.
So, you can add this property into
application.property file
spring.kafka.consumer.properties.
metadata.max.age.milliseconds.
So, this is important. Metadata max age
millisecond. Okay? So, default is 5
minutes.
So, after every 5 minutes consumer
refresh the metadata. If you want less
time, you can change it.
On-demand refresh is let's say that
consumer
reach to the broker
and ask for hey
this is partition 23. This is the topic
order-events.
Can [snorts] you return me the
events? But if this broker say that hey,
I am not a leader of this partition.
So, means
consumer has wrong information. So,
on-demand. So, it will initiate the
refresh immediately.
Okay?
Step four.
Once it has the metadata, what it
generally do is that
it finds the group coordinator from the
metadata. Okay, so partition 23 of check
which broker
is the leader for this for this topic
consumer offsets partition 23. Which
broker is the leader? That leader act as
a
group coordinator which performs or
which take care of all the things for
this group notification group.
So, what it do is it request contains
hey
So, this consumer say that hey group
coordinator
I want to join this group and this is
the topic I want to subscribe.
So, what all the possible doubts can
come is that consumer request
to join more than one topic. There can
be many consumer in a group.
Different topic, different consumer
different topic. So,
we have already covered all these three
in depth. Okay, in a as a separate
dedicated video. Kindly check it out.
Step five.
Partition assignment. What group
coordinator will do is that okay, you
want to join topic order-events.
Okay? So, what group coordinator will do
is that it will assign a particular
partition of a topic to a
particular consumer in a group.
Okay? So, the question which can come
here is that how partitions are divided
among group in
among consumer in the group?
See, if you find this that I am going
very fast in this step because we have
already discussed this flow multiple
times. Okay? Because you can say that in
consumer setup part one
part two, part three, we have already
gone through these steps. So, that's why
I am going little fast over these step.
All I want to focus on the doubts.
So, how group coordinator
decides or you can say that divide the
partition of a topic among the consumer?
What are the
algorithm?
So, see.
These are the four algorithms. Important
one. The first one is range assigner.
This is the default.
Take this
example consumer
C1, C2, C3. Three consumer.
And for this topic, let's say there are
total six partitions.
So, this algorithm what it does is it
first sort this consumer and partition.
So, okay, let's say it sort the consumer
alphabetically. It sort the partition
numeric order. Okay?
After that, what it will do is it do
this formula. Partitions divide by
consumers. So,
there are six partition, three consumer.
Each one will get two. So, it will give
P0, P1 to consumer one.
P2, P3 to consumer two.
P4, P5 to consumer three.
So, that's it is algorithm.
Range. It gives a range
to a particular consumers.
Round robin is like very simple. The
same example. So, we have three
consumer. Consumer one, consumer two,
consumer three. So, what it will do is
it give iterate over the partition. It
will give one to each. So, P0 here
P1 to consumer two.
Partition two to consumer three. Like
similarly we P3 to consumer one.
P4 to consumer two.
P5 to consumer three. Likewise. If there
are more
like this, it can go.
Okay?
Round robin.
Sticky. These two are important. Sticky
and cooperative sticky.
So, the same example. So, in a sticky
assigner, what generally happen is
starting you can say that it happens
with round robin itself. So, it start
um the same what round robin does, it
does the same thing. But its major
advantage comes during rebalance.
Okay? So, now let's say that any
consumer removed
from the group or new consumer added in
the group.
Then the rebalance has to be done,
right?
So, that's where
its advantage comes into the picture.
So, let's see that when rebalance
happen.
Okay? Let's say C1, C2, C3. These are
the partition assigned to them.
C3 got crashed. This is got crashed.
So, if you are following these two
algorithm range assigner and round
robin, what would have happened?
Every consumer. So, this is crashed.
So, these two, every consumer which are
alive
consumer one, consumer two
drop the partition they were allotted.
So, consumer one has now no partition.
Consumer two has now no partition.
Every consumer is stop reading because
now they don't
don't have any partition assigned.
The algorithm runs full recalculation
from a start for the remaining two
consumer. This is generally in this case
range assigner and round robin.
Okay?
So, the problem is that
earlier C1 has P0 and P3. So, here if
you see earlier
consumer has these two topics. Now, what
we did is that hey
rebalance is going to run. First, drop
your partition. So, it remove P0. It
remove P3. It So, it just not only
partition. Consumer also has to now drop
or clear its cache or any other
information it hold about this
partition.
And then algorithm runs and possibly
totally different partition might be
assigned to
C1. Okay?
So, there is a lot of clearance or you
can say that lot of movement happens
in case of range assigner and round
robin.
But in case of sticky
the advantage is that
it is more smarter.
During rebalance, it try to achieve the
even distribution. Okay, that's its main
goal.
But it try to keep the consumer attached
to the partition they already had. So,
let's say consumer one already has P0
P3. Consumer two already has P1 P4.
Now, C3 crashed. What it does is
instead of like, "Hey,
everyone drop your partition." What it
will do that
it just divide whatever the partition
consumer three has. It just divide among
those
available consumers.
So, it able to achieve
equal distribution. Plus, there is less
movement of partition. So, let's say
consumer one already has some cash for
P0 P3 and lot other information. So,
that will remain intact. All it has to
build is for P2.
But for
range assigner and round robin, they
have to drop their partition fully.
Total rebalance happen. New partition
they might have got totally different.
And they might have to do the clearance
and build the same cash and all for all
new partition they have assigned.
So, you got it?
And what's cooperative sticky? So, it is
very much similar to a sticky.
Okay, but there is one difference.
So, range assigner, round robin, and
sticky assigner all are eager
rebalancer.
What does eager rebalancer mean? When
rebalance happens, consumer stop reading
from the partitions.
Okay?
Till new enrollments are assigned.
In all these three, when the rebalance
happen,
consumer stop
for some time. They don't read it
till the rebalance completed. Okay?
But in the cooperative sticky, what
happen is it follows cooperative
protocol.
So, it follows in two steps. Step one,
algorithm decide old partition which
consumer will still hold, similar to a
sticky assigner. In a sticky assigner,
it
try to see that as many partition it can
still
stick to the old consumer itself. So,
that's what it also do that, "Hey,
what all the partition
old partition which consumer can still
hold?"
Okay? So,
on those partition, consumer can still
make the read calls. So, it don't
completely stop.
Okay?
It don't completely stop. So, let's say
that in this case earlier, consumer one
has P0 P1.
Consumer two has P2 P3.
Okay?
Now, and consumer three has let's say P4
P5. The same example which we have taken
and this got crashed.
Now, in the step one it say that, "Okay,
for C1, this two will hold. They can
stick to it. For C2, this two can stick.
Only thing is P4 need to be assigned
here and P5 need to be assigned here.
So, step one it able to decide just
which
partitions are sticking to their
previous consumer.
So, this consumer can continuously read
from this partition.
Only read from this partition four and
partition five till their assignment is
happening. That would be stopped. So, P4
P5 here. So, no read from partition four
and partition five is supported.
Once it is assigned, then only after
consumer supported, updated, and then
supported it.
So, there is you can say that
uh better or you can say that much
uh you will find less lag in the
cooperative sticky approach.
Okay? And how we can set into our uh
this
algorithm? Again, in the
application.properties itself.
So, Kafka consumer properties here.
Partition assignment strategy.
Partition.assignment.strategy.
Okay? Whichever you want. Range assigner
or round robin assigner or sticky
assigner or cooperative sticky assigner.
Generally, this is the recommended one.
But this is the default.
Okay. Now, step six and step seven, what
consumer does is that it assigned a
partition. Now, in step six, what it
will do is consumer ask group
coordinator
till where the offset is read for this
partition P0, let's say. For this offset
order-events,
consumer one has to read partition P0.
Now, it will ask coordinator, "Hey, from
which offset I need to start?"
So, what's the question can come? What
if there is no offset present into the
uh consumer _offsets topic? There is no
offset present. What would happen?
So, understand this flow.
Group coordinator perform this step to
determine what to return.
So, consumer receive partition
assignment order event partition zero.
Consumer ask group coordinator, "Hey,
give me the offset information."
Now, two possibility. Offset
information present into consumer offset
topic? Yes or no? If yes,
return it. "Hey,
from offset 23, you need to start."
Okay, very simple.
But if offset information is not
present,
then this configuration is important.
So, this is you can say that an
instructor to the group coordinator.
Auto offset reset, whether it's a
latest, none, or earliest.
So, by default is latest. If you don't
set it, by default is latest latest.
So, what does it mean is consumer read
only new records after the partition
assignment. Okay? Let's say that
partition P0
already has 500 offsets.
Okay? But
there is no information present into
this topic. Okay? First time consumer is
coming. But the producer has already
published so many offsets, let's say.
So, now since there is no offset present
and let's say I haven't put this
configuration into consumer
auto-offset.reset, so default is latest.
So, when consumer is up,
a partition is assigned P0. So, it will
not read this 500 whatever available
into the log.
So, now after this assignment, any new
request comes in, then only it will
read.
Okay? Earliest means
like
from the available earliest offset.
Okay? So, let's say this log log file
has 500 offsets, so it will start from
uh start in this log. Okay? Earliest.
Why I mentioned that after cleanup?
Because there is a time-to-time cleanup
happens, right? You remember? So, after
cleanup, whatever the earliest present,
it will start from there and it consumer
will read all the available
offsets.
You can also set none. None means that
if offset information is not present
into this topic,
throw exception.
Okay? So, you can choose depend upon
your business logic what you are
building.
Okay, step eight and nine.
Now, what will do consumer invokes the
broker leader
for let's say order-events
partition P0.
Whichever the broker is a leader, this
consumer will invoke it and say that,
"Hey, return me the
return me the events. Return me the
events. Okay?
So,
question is,
what if there is no event?
How much time consumer will wait for the
broker?
Okay?
Remember,
Kafka consumer is a single threaded.
It process the record one by one.
Okay? And if you remember from the
previous video,
I explained this poll.
Okay? So, now let's say your consumer
one,
the partition assigned to it, let's say
order-events,
it need to read P0 P1. Okay? And this
both partition leader is broker one
broker one.
Similarly, it also assigned
payment-events
partition zero and its leader is broker
two.
So, what generally in poll what happen
is
it create a connection with all the
brokers
and send only one fetch request. So, it
will send one request to the broker one
and ask for, "Hey, give me for order
events, give me the records for
partition zero and partition one
from this this offsets."
Similarly, it will send only one request
to broker two.
Okay? They will send the response back.
It merge the response into consumer
records and then one by one it will
iterate.
So, this we have already seen. Now, the
question is that what if this broker is
taking some time?
So, how much time this consumer will
wait for the response?
The one thing is you can set this into
configuration. spring.kafka.listener.
poll-timeout.
So, this poll timeout we can set.
Okay? After 5 seconds,
whatever the record I have, only if this
broker has sent the response, it's okay.
Proceed with that itself.
Okay?
Another doubt which can come is in one
poll, how much data is sent?
Okay. What if there are massive amount
of data or there is no data? How much
data is sent?
We know that consumer can ask a broker
to return from multiple partitions. I
already told you that it can ask a
broker that it return from partition
zero, partition one. Okay?
And it can also ask multiple brokers at
the same time also.
Okay?
So, how much data broker will send in
one fetch request?
In I'm talking about one fetch request.
So,
see this. This is
very interesting.
So, first configuration is
in the consumer we can add is
max.partition.fetch.byte.
Okay, default is let's say 1 MB.
So,
the fetch request which comes. Let's say
this is the fetch request which our
consumer has sent.
Topic A,
I am interested in partition zero and
partition one. For topic B, I am
interested in partition one. Okay? So,
this is the broker one. This request has
reached.
So, and this broker one is the leader of
this topic, topic A, topic B. And the
partition is P0, P1. So, for this topic,
these two partitions, broker one is
leader. Similarly, for topic B,
partition one, broker one is the leader.
So, this consumer send one request to
fetch the records from all three
partitions of two topic.
So, this first configuration,
max.partition.fetch.bytes.
Partition fetch byte.
So, from each partition,
what is the maximum amount of bytes can
be fetched? Remember, network only knows
bytes. How much bytes I can fetch? Okay?
So, default is 1 MB. So, from partition
zero, maximum you can fetch is 1 MB.
Partition one, maximum you can fetch is
1 MB. Partition one of topic B, maximum
you can fetch is 1 MB. So, that is
first way to control.
Another way is that fetch.max.byte.
Okay? So, this is individual partition.
But, after that,
broker will send the response, right?
The combine of all
partition zero, partition one, and the
topic B, partition one. It will combine
and send the response. So, after
combining, what should be the maximum
size?
Maximum size is 52 MB.
Okay? So, you can say that this is
another level of filter that okay, from
each partition, maximum you can take out
1 MB, but after combining everything, it
should be less than 52 MB only. This is
the maximum limit you have to send.
Cool? So, this is the second
configuration.
After that, broker decide when to
respond. So, it has already fetched the
data.
Now, it has to send the response to the
consumer.
So, the first is that
fetch.minimum.byte
equals to one.
So,
one thing is that
condition one is data accumulated
greater than equals to min byte,
send response to the consumer.
Okay? So, this is one condition.
As soon as after this So, it has fetched
from this partition, fetched from this
partition, fetched from this partition.
Also, this overall size of this is less
than 52 MB.
So, now it has collected all the data.
Now, it is waiting.
Uh shall I send the response or wait?
So, it uses this. Okay, if minimum byte
set is one. Yes, I have more than that.
Send it. It will not wait.
But here, let's say you have sent
minimum byte I want is let's say
uh 30.
Uh 30 bytes. Something.
But here, let's say only you have
collected five bytes till now. There is
very less traffic.
Okay?
So, it wait. But how much time? Then you
can add more.
Max.wait.millisecond is
500, which is like 5 second. Fi- 0.5
second. So, after 500 millisecond,
whatever it has, it will send it.
Send to the consumer.
So, clear?
So, we have a restriction how much max
we can fetch from a particular
partition.
From one broker,
response overall how much maximum broke
one broker
response size could be.
Minimum byte is like once the broker has
fetched,
if this is the minimum byte limit reach,
it can free to send the response.
But if this limit is not reach, it
doesn't have to wait forever. It only
has to wait this much amount of time to
get more data. If no data comes,
send it anyway whatever it has.
Even if it is less than minimum bytes.
Okay? After that, consumer
get the data.
Okay?
So, now here last configuration is that
So, after poll,
let's say consumer get 2,000
records
in 50 MB.
So, I told you over the network,
everything is
bytes in this MB, KB, and all, right?
So, it's not like 200 record, 500
record, 2,000 records. Nothing like
that.
So, now let's say broker has
returned 50 MB in response.
Now, this response might contain 2,000
records.
Okay?
So, there is one more configuration.
Max.poll.record 500. So, at a time, I
will just pick 500 records out of this
200. So, this 200 by default is is
stored in a buffer
within consumer itself.
Okay? So, consumer is stored in a
buffer.
So,
the poll response will [snorts] take out
500 out of this first.
Okay? And one by one, you will iterate
over it. You can perform your at the
rate Kafka listener. Done? And after
this everything done, you can commit
offsets. And after that, you will do
poll again. And when you do poll again,
it will not make another network call.
It If there is a more data into the
buffer, it will fetch out next 500 byte.
Okay? This records That much record it
will fetch.
Okay? So, it give first preference to
the buffer.
So, that's what I have explained here.
Let's say that a buff- broker has
returned more records.
So, those will be stored into the
internal buffer of the consumer.
And based on this property,
max.poll.records,
that many records would be fetched from
the buffer.
You will work on it.
And in the next poll again, it will
first check buffer only. If records
present in there,
use it.
Don't make a network call to the broker.
Cool?
So, this configuration is also clear?
Okay. Now, another doubt which can come
is
Okay,
we do poll.
And when we process the data, we again
do poll. Is it possible to have a gap
between polls? Yes.
So, you can add this configuration.
Idle-between-polls
zero. By default is zero means no As
soon as you finish the work, commit the
offset, again do poll. But if you want
more, this is in millisecond. You can
add millisecond if you want difference.
But make sure that there is no lag.
Okay? So, based upon your company,
project, business logic,
deal with this configuration.
Okay? Another question can come is
how to know if consumer is stuck while
processing the event or any other issue
with the consumer? So, poll has done.
Now, consumer is working.
How broker will know that hey, consumer
is up
or stuck or crashed?
So, there are certain configurations.
So, these two configurations used
together.
heartbeat.interval.millisecond.
Okay? So, this means that consumer will
send
heartbeat pulse to group coordinator
every 3 second.
Okay? So, you can say that this
configuration is for consumer that hey,
every 3 second, a background thread runs
which send the
pulse to the group coordinator.
That hey, I am alive.
And this configuration,
session.timeout.millisecond.
So, this is for you can say that for
group coordinator. Good group
coordinator will wait for the heartbeat
this much amount of time. So, generally,
this the amount of time is greater than
this. Sometime, it is possible that
pulse got missed. It's not like consumer
is
uh crashed. So, that's why
session.timeout.millisecond
is generally higher than this.
But this is the amount of time. Let's
say here 45 second, group coordinator
will wait for the heartbeat.
If after this much time also, heartbeat
do not arrive,
then group coordinator will assume that
consumer is crashed.
Okay? Another possibility is that
consumer is properly sending the
heartbeat.
Okay? To the group coordinator every 3
second. Every 3 second, heartbeat is
there. So, means consumer is alive.
But what if there is no poll request?
So, let's say in the previous poll
request itself, it got 500 record, and
it is keep on processing.
But there is no poll request. How group
coordinator will know that is it stuck
here like an infinite loop, for example?
Is it stuck here?
Or what should I do?
So, there are certain configurations
like here
max poll interval millisecond.
Okay, so here what we are saying is that
group coordinator expect one poll call
every 5 minutes. So this is millisecond
so like 5 minutes.
Okay, group coordinator
will expect one poll request every 5
minutes.
If after 5 minutes
poll request doesn't come, it can assume
that consumer got stuck and it will
initiate the rebalance.
Got it?
Okay, step 10, consumer process the
events. Okay, now it does the polling,
it got the event, now it has to process
the event. So during process the event
exception can come like during
deserialization, during process the
event which we have already discussed in
the previous video. Okay, you can check
it out.
So step 11 is offset commit. Now you
have already processed the event, you
have to commit the offset. So how to
manage the offset?
So for auto commit
you have to put this enable \hyphen}
auto commit equals to true.
Okay.
And after how much time or frequency you
can set auto commit interval
milliseconds 5 second. This is in
millisecond.
So background thread will run
and you can say that whenever poll will
happen it check
auto commit is true
and
this interval
limit is crossed
now whatever the offset till this offset
event is fetch
commit it.
Okay.
But for manual commit we have to disable
this
enable \hyphen} auto commit you have to
make it false
and there is something called
acknowledge mode.
So there are different acknowledge mode.
Okay, this is the default.
So in the default what generally happen
is let's say during poll you get 500
records.
You will process all the records
and after processing all the records
commit once will happen. So no auto
commit, it's like a batch. After 500
record only
this commit has to be happen.
Okay, internally framework code already
has the logic to commit it. Okay.
But only thing is now we are controlling
that hey we don't want auto commit like
based on time. Okay, we want some
control. So the control is like I am
disabling the auto
and the control I am is like one is
batch.
After poll, whatever the records I got,
once those are processed, then only
commit it.
Another is
record.
So for each record, earlier it is batch,
right? So poll get 500 records, after
500 records it send one commit request.
In record, for each record, once you get
a record, process it, success, commit
it. So you have to more commit overhead
is there in it.
Then it is time.
So in the time in the sense acknowledge
mode is your time.
And you can also send the interval
acknowledge time.
So commit every 5 second. So it is again
a manual
but you can say that interval.
Commit every 5 second.
We can also have a count based
acknowledgement mode count and the count
is 10. Commit after every 10 records.
Once you process the 10 records
successfully, commit it.
Then manual.
Even we can if you can also set manual.
Then in the manual way what we can do is
that during Kafka listener, we have a
Kafka listener, right? So in that we can
in parameter we can add this
acknowledgement.
Okay, and once your business logic is
completed successfully, you have to
acknowledge acknowledge dot
acknowledge method. You have to invoke
it.
But
it is similar to batch.
So let's say a poll has 500 records.
Okay.
So now after so you know that this
method would be invoked for each record.
So for each record you have invoked this
manual commit acknowledge method.
But with this mode
it won't send
500 times. You can say that it will wait
for the batch to complete. Once the
batch is complete, then only it will
send one manual
acknowledge commit.
So there is a different version of this
manual \hyphen} immediate.
Okay, very same same code but only
difference is that like you have 500
record
for each record this method will get
invoked and whenever you invoke it for
each record this commit would be
initiated.
And this is I would say that
generally
I have like if you have work with Kafka
and more, generally if you don't have
any very specific reason
many will not play with all this one.
Batch is something which is sufficient.
Okay, so generally this is the record
count
which you can set. How many records, you
know, small small batch like 50, 100 you
can
in one poll you can
you want to deal with.
Okay, but depend again
project to project, business logic, but
yeah, just wanted to give a heads up
that there are even if we disable the
auto commit
okay, there are different ways
through which we can control when the
commit should have happen.
Okay, so these are the different steps
on which different doubts and interview
question can come and with that
I am done like for Kafka consumer part I
am done and
next I will start with the transaction.
Transaction in
Kafka.
Okay, this is also important part.
Okay, guys, thank you. Bye.